{"tossups": [{"question": "A minister with this surname withdrew his support for the Salem witch trials after his wife, Sarah, was accused. Another man with this surname wrote about the effects of treason accusations on Philip Nolan in A Man Without a Country. Another man with this surname was captured at Flushing Bay following the Battle of Long Island. That man said \u201cI only regret that I have but one life to lose for my country.\u201d For ten points, give this surname of the Revolutionary War spy, Nathan.", "answer": "<em><b> Hale</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man flayed his daughter\u2019s lovers after accusations of adultery in the Nesle\u2019s Tower affair. This man\u2019s claims to supremacy were repudiated in the Unam sanctam, prompting him to send Guillaume de Nogaret to arrest Boniface VIII. This king burned Jacques de Molay at the stake in an attempt to curb the power of the Knights Templar. Clement V was elected pope during this man\u2019s reign, beginning the Avignon papacy. For ten points, name this French king named for his handsomeness.", "answer": "<em><b> Philip IV</b></em> (accept<em><b> Philip the Fair</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Charles Moose resigned as a leading investigator into this event after his police department banned him from making a book deal about it titled Three Weeks in October. A stolen Bushmaster XM-15 was used in these attacks, which resulted in a death sentence for John Allen Muhammad. Lee Boyd Malvo was a juvenile perpetrator of this event, whose first victim was shot in Rockville, Maryland. For ten points, name these 2002 attacks that affected the metropolitan area of the U.S. capital.", "answer": "Washington<em><b> D.C. sniper</b></em> attacks (accept<em><b> Beltway sniper</b></em>, accept<em><b> District of Columbia </b><b>sniper</b></em> attacks)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This person defended assassin Leon Czolgosz [CHOW-gaw] as a \u201csupersensitive being.\u201d The last twelve chapters of a work by this author about the Kronstadt Rebellion were removed entirely by Doubleday, Page & Co., resulting in her book My Further Disillusionment in Russia. In response to World War One, this editor of the journal Mother Earth co-founded the No Conscription League with Alexander Berkman who tried to assassinate Henry Clay Frick. For ten points, name this Lithuanian-born anarchist.", "answer": "Emma<em><b> Goldman</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "KKK activities in this state were the target of the FBI\u2019s COINTELPRO-WHITE HATE program. In this state, three CORE workers were found dead under a dam. In 1964, delegates from this state to the Democratic National Convention created this state\u2019s namesake Freedom Democratic Party. A riot broke out in Oxford after James Meredith attempted to enroll at this state\u2019s namesake university. Freedom Summer occurred in, for ten points, what state that was described as \u201cburning\u201d during the Civil Rights Movement?", "answer": "<em><b> Mississippi</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This empire was splintered into the Joma and Hamana spheres shortly after its final ruler, Mahmud IV, was defeated at the Battle of Djenne. Another ruler of this empire allegedly founded it after using a rooster-tipped arrow at the battle of Kirina to defeat Sumanguru. Sundiata Keita ruled this empire, another ruler of which allegedly inflated the price of gold along the Mediterranean after his lavish spending while on the hajj. Mansa Musa was a ruler of, for ten points, what West African empire?", "answer": "<em><b> Mali</b></em> Empire (accept<em><b> Manden</b></em> Kurufaba, accept<em><b> Nyeni</b></em>))", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "While serving as a self described, \u201coppressed assistant professor,\u201d this man wrote an essay about calculating interest rates for goods traveling at light speeds. This economist argued that there were parallels in economic policy between 2008 and 1929 in The Return of Depression Economics. This winner of the 2008 Nobel Prize in Economics described U.S. foreign policies in The Great Unravelling. For ten points, name this economist and columnist for the New York Times.", "answer": "Paul<em><b> Krugman</b></em>", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "A three-day retreat to this location, known as the Alberich Maneuver, was cited in propaganda as \u201cHun barbarism.\u201d A decision to create this position \u201cwas not reached without a painful struggle,\u201daccording to Erich Ludendorff, who started building it after the Battle of the Somme. The Siegfried Line was one section of, for ten points, what system of artillery, blockhouses, and trenches built during World War One, named for a Field Marshal who later became the German president?", "answer": "<em><b> Hindenburg Line</b></em> (accept \u201cPosition\u201d in place of \u201cLine,\u201d accept<em><b> Siegfriedstellung</b></em> or <em><b>Siegfried Line</b></em>/Position before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Alberta\u2019s Newbrook Observatory was the first to photograph this object whose sighting was an initial goal of Operation Moonwatch. Sergei Korolev proposed the original plan for developing this object, and its prototype, \u201cObject D,\u201d was deemed too complicated to meet the early-1957 deadline. This object\u2019s three week mission was a major blow to the U.S. in the Space Race. For ten points, name this Soviet artificial satellite, the first ever launched into space.", "answer": "<em><b> Sputnik</b></em> 1", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "Larry McDonald attempted to impeach an African-American holder of this position. The first woman to hold this position defended anti-communist dictatorships in her namesake doctrine. One holder of this position was ready to wait for an answer to a question he posed to Valerian Zorin \u201cuntil Hell freezes over.\u201dA woman who was initially hesitant to label the Hutu-Tutsi conflict as a genocide held this post. For ten points, name this position held by Andrew Young and Madeleine Albright.", "answer": "<em><b> U</b></em> nited<em><b> S</b></em>tates<em><b> Ambassador</b></em> to the<em><b> U</b></em> nited<em><b> N</b></em> ations", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A no-confidence vote against this politician failed despite its support from Herbert Hupka. This politician was popular with the student-led APO, who had grown dissatisfied with his conservative predecessor Kurt Kiesinger. This politician resigned after his aide, Gunter Guillaume, was exposed as a Stasi spy. This leader signed the Basic Treaty, which began to normalize relations with an eastern neighbor. For ten points, name this West German chancellor who proposed the conciliatory Ostpolitik.", "answer": "Willy<em><b> Brandt</b></em> (accept Herbert<em><b> Frahm</b></em>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "At a meeting in this state, John Cotton Smith claimed that its central group had to deal with \u201ca formidable and exasperated enemy.\u201d A group of Massachusetts attendees to a meeting in this state was known as the Essex Junto. Timothy Pickering attended a meeting in this state that called for an end to a concept that was believed to favor the Jeffersonian Democratic-Republicans, the three-fifths compromise. For ten points, name this state that hosted the Federalists at the Hartford Convention.", "answer": "<em><b> Connecticut</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s first project was an adaptation of farces by the Roman playwright, Plautus. This man won a Pulitzer Prize for a work that revolves around a fictionalized version of Georges Seurat. In 2004, a production by this man won five Tony Awards and starred Neil Patrick Harris as Lee Harvey Oswald. For ten points, name this creator of A Funny Thing Happened on the Way to the Forum, Sunday in the Park with George, and Assassins.", "answer": "Stephen<em><b> Sondheim</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "Almost four minutes of the film The President\u2019s Last Band depicting this man were censored after his son sued. This man faced the Bu-Ma riots and passed the Yushin Constitution. This man\u2019s friend, Kim Jae-gyu, the head of the Korean CIA, assassinated this man in 1979. Unit 124 tried to kill this man in the Blue House Raid. The \u201cMiracle on the Han River\u201d was led by, for ten points, what president of South Korea whose daughter, also a president of South Korea, is now in jail for bribery?", "answer": "<em><b> Park Chung-hee</b></em>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Tupac Shakur mourned this woman in his song \u201cHellrazor,\u201d stating that she \u201cnever got to see the bullet, just heard the shot.\u201d An Ice Cube song that includes the line \u201cSo pay respect to the black fist / Or we\u2019ll burn your store right down to a crisp\u201d was inspired by the murder of this woman who allegedly stole a bottle of orange juice. The song \u201cBlack Korea\u201d was inspired by the death of, for ten points, what 15-year-old girl who was murdered by Soon Ja Du in the buildup to the Rodney King riots?", "answer": "Latasha<em><b> Harlins</b></em>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "While entering Naples, this man was given Bernini\u2019s Boy with a Dragon. Charters giving power to regions of Aragon were taken away by this king\u2019s Nueva Planta decrees. This man\u2019s rule was broken into two by the seven-month reign of Louis I. Louis XIV declared that if the Petit Dauphin, Louis, died this man would have to surrender the throne, leading to the War of the Spanish Succession. For ten points, name this successor to Charles II, the first Bourbon king of Spain.", "answer": "<em><b> Philip V</b></em> (accept<em><b> Felipe V</b></em> )", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "While fighting the Amorites, this man commanded the sun and moon to stand still in the sky. Along with Caleb, this son of Nun was the only one of the spies to support invading Canaan. Modern scholarship suggests that this man\u2019s namesake book is not historically accurate but rather is meant to detail obedience to the law. For ten points, name this successor of Moses, the Biblical leader of the Hebrews at the legendary Battle of Jericho.", "answer": "<em><b> Joshua</b></em> (accept<em><b> Jehoshua</b></em>, accept<em><b> Hoshea</b></em>)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {}, {"question": "This battle nearly turned thanks to a a woody 600-yard gap undefended by the men of James Lane and James Archer. An offensive, prompted by this battle\u2019s result, became bogged down in heavy winter rains and was subsequently called the Mud March. This battle hinged upon James Longstreet\u2019s defense of a stone wall. For ten points, name this battle of late 1862 in which Robert E. Lee thwarted a Union attempt to cross the Rappahannock.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Fredericksburg</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>During a speech at West Point, this man controversially said, \u201cGreat Britain has lost an empire and has not yet found a role.\u201d This man won the 1970 Pulitzer Prize for History for his memoir of his time serving in his highest post titled (+) Present at the Creation. This Secretary of State\u2019s tenure during the Communist Party\u2019s expulsion of the Kuomintang led critics to blame him for the \u201closs of China.\u201d The formation of (*) </b> NATO occurred during this man\u2019s tenure and he helped outline a president\u2019s doctrine providing financial aid to opponents of communism. For ten points, name this Secretary of State under Truman.", "answer": "Dean<em><b> Acheson</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>During this battle, Auguste de Caulaincourt was killed in a cavalry charge against the Raevsky Redoubt which absorbed much of the French assault during this battle. The (+) Bagration [buh-gruh-tee-ON] fleches were a system of fortifications created for this battle by the namesake Georgian prince who was killed during it. The winning commander\u2019s refusal to commit the (*)</b> Imperial Guard in this battle is considered by some historians to have thrown away his victory. For ten points, name this 1812 engagement outside Moscow, the climactic battle of Napoleon\u2019s invasion of Russia.", "answer": "Battle of<em><b> Borodino</b></em>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>These men are depicted as incredibly tall next to picketers in a mosaic at Syracuse University. These two men rest in coffins in a painting which depicts Judge Webster (+) Thayer taking an oath in a portrait in the background. \u201cThe Passion\u201d of these two men is the subject of a Ben Shahn painting. A series of ballads to these men, including \u201cTwo Good Men\u201d and \u201cYou Souls of (*) </b> Boston,\u201d was written by Woody Guthrie. Convicted of the murder of Alessandro Berardelli and Frederick Parmenter, for ten points, name these two Italian anarchists executed in 1927.", "answer": "Nicola<em><b> Sacco</b></em> and Bartolomeo<em><b> Vanzetti</b></em>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>Stuart Goldman\u2019s best-selling book focuses on this battle and its effects on World War Two. Grievances from the Changkufeng Incident a year before this battle were a leading cause of it. The first mass-scale use of (+) airpower for a military purpose is sometimes cited as this battle\u2019s Nomonhan Incident. Georgy Zhukov came to prominence at this battle that arose after disputes concerning whether the namesake river dividing (*)</b> Manchuria and Mongolia constituted an international boundary. For ten points, name this 1939 battle along the border of the Soviet Union and Japan.", "answer": "Battle(s) of<em><b> Khalkhin Gol</b></em> (accept Battle of<em><b> Nomonhan</b></em> or<em><b> Nomonhan</b></em> Incident before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A character from this city dreams of owning a video store and sells stolen refrigerators to raise money. Memphis Lee demands 10,000 dollars to sell his restaurant in the play Two Trains Running which is set in this city\u2019s (+) Hill District. Another character from this city notes that \u201cJackie Robinson wasn\u2019t nobody.\u201d That character, Troy Maxson, is barred from driving this city\u2019s garbage trucks in the play (*)</b> Fences. For ten points, name this city, the setting of a namesake cycle of plays by August Wilson intended to describe the Black experience in 20th century America.", "answer": "<em><b> Pittsburgh</b></em>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Drama"}, {"question": "<b>This man, whose appointment to West Point was legendarily secured by Abraham Lincoln, fled to Canada after worrying that his execution of twenty-two men after the Battle of New Bern might be seen as a war crime. This man and two cavalry commanders were reportedly having a fish fry when the Battle of (+) Five Forks broke out. Lewis Armistead died while commanding a brigade under this general who reportedly told Robert E. Lee, \u201cI have (*)</b> no division\u201d after a disastrous attack on Cemetery Ridge. For ten points, name this Confederate general who led his namesake charge at the Battle of Gettysburg.", "answer": "George<em><b> Pickett</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>According to Josephus, Herod the Great captured this city and built a fortress on its plateau. Inhabitants of this city allegedly set everything but food stockpiles on fire to show that they had the means to choose survival. This city, to which the (+) narrow Snake Path led, was taken by Lucius Silva\u2019s Fretensis legion after a ramp was constructed in order to allow for the use of a siege tower. After Roman troops succeeded in capturing this location, a large number of Sicarii rebels from the (*) </b> Zealot faction committed suicide. For ten points, name this heavily defended Jewish fortress atop a large hilltop in Israel.", "answer": "<em><b> Masada</b></em>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>One of this man\u2019s successors as consul, Quintus Fabius Vibulanus, was named by Appius Claudius as part of the second set of decemviri. This man unsuccessfully summoned the plebeian Spurius (+) Maelius, leading Gaius Servius Ahala to kill Maelius. This man\u2019s behavior after defeating the Aequi at the Battle of Mount Algidus inspired Henry Knox to name a (*) </b> society after him to assist the families of Continental Army soldiers and sailors. For ten points, name this virtuous Roman farmer and statesman who twice relinquished his dictatorial power once threats to Rome were vanquished.", "answer": "Lucius Quinctius<em><b> Cincinnatus</b></em>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This person was criticized for his reluctance to tell David Cicilline that accepting foreign election assistance was inappropriate. This person denied that the replacement of Geoffrey (+) Berman was intended to stall cases in the Southern District of New York. Faculty from this man\u2019s alma mater signed a letter condemning him for \u201cundermining the rule of law.\u201d This man authored a summary and subsequent selective redaction of the (*)</b> Mueller Report. For ten points, name this man who served twice as US Attorney General, having been appointed by George H.W. Bush in 1991 and by Donald Trump in 2019.", "answer": "William<em><b> Barr</b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}